<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright (c) 2010-2012 mgouyett.
  INRIA-IRISA- Triskell Team
  All rights reserved. This program and the accompanying materials
  are made available under the terms of the Eclipse Public License v1.0
  which accompanies this distribution, and is available at
  http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html
  
  Contributors:
      mgouyett - initial API and implementation
  	INRIA-IRISA- Triskell Team
  	contact : marie.gouyette@gmail.com
-->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book lang="en-US">
  <?ooogenerator OpenOffice.org/2.0$Linux OpenOffice.org_project/680m1$Build-8990?>
  <?oooversion?>
  <bookinfo>
    <pubdate>Build date: @BUILD.DATE@</pubdate>
    <date>Last modification: $Date:: 2010-05-25 08:39:54#$</date>
    <author>
      <firstname> Marie Gouyette</firstname>
      <firstname/>
    </author>
    <title>Selection and Product Derivation Engine Technical documentation</title>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>Feature Diagram Editor</keyword>
      <keyword>metamodeling</keyword>
      <keyword>Domain specific language (DSL)</keyword>
    </keywordset>
    <subtitle> </subtitle>
    <bibliomisc>Licence EPL</bibliomisc>
    <bibliomisc/>
    <abstract>
      <para>This documentation presents the technical documentation about selection engine and
        product derivation for Feature Diagram Editor and the tests, which takes part of the ANR
        Project MOVIDA. </para>
    </abstract>
    <publisher>
      <publishername>INRIA</publishername>
      <address>
        <state>France</state>
        <otheraddr>
          <ulink url="http://www.inria.fr">http://www.inria.fr</ulink>
        </otheraddr>
      </address>
    </publisher>
    <confgroup>
      <conftitle>title</conftitle>
      <confnum>Reference</confnum>
      <confsponsor>sponsor</confsponsor>
    </confgroup>
  </bookinfo>
  <preface>
    <?print-orientation portrait?>
    <title>Preface</title>
    <para>Product Derivation is a way in the Software Product Line (SPL) to obtain a particular
      product model (a<emphasis role="bold"> resolved model</emphasis>) from a global model
        <emphasis role="bold">(base model</emphasis>) on which variability (a way to model common
      and variable parts of a given architecture) is defined on a <emphasis role="bold">variability
        model</emphasis> (in our case a feature model).</para>
    <para> Here we have two tools : <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Selection Engine </emphasis>: It permits to an end-user to
            select desired features and stores all of these choices on a model called <emphasis
              role="bold">resolution model</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Product Derivation Engine</emphasis> : it use this resolved
            model to create the product model <emphasis role="bold">(resolved
            model</emphasis>).</para>
          <para>This graphical tool regroup these two tools to integrate them on the Feature Diagram
            Editor.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
    <para> It is an extension of the Feature Diagram Editor that permits to user to choose desired
      features and store it on a resolution model (Selection Engine) and then obtain resolved model
      from this resolution model (Product Derivation Engine). For more information about it please
      refer to the Product Derivation Documentation on the Eclipse help and on the <ulink
        url="http://movida.gforge.inria.fr/uploads/Demos/SelectionAndDerivationDemo.htm"> sample
        wink video
        http://movida.gforge.inria.fr/uploads/Demos/SelectionAndDerivationDemo.htm</ulink>. </para>
    <para>Please also refer to <ulink
        url="@ONLINE.OR.LOCAL@/fr.inria.featureDiagramEditor.doc/help/@OUTPUT.VERSION@/Movida-ProductDerivationEngine-Technical-Documentation/index.html"
        > end-user documentation</ulink> .</para>
  </preface>
  <chapter>
    <title>Installation</title>
    <para>To install Selection Engine and Product Derivation Engine you need to select Feature
      Diagram Editor category on the Movida Studio update site and all of its dependencies and
      select Product Derivation and Selection Engine. In this case, Selection Engine and Product
      Derivation Engine are dependant from Feature Diagram Editor. </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Metamodel used and choices made</title>
    <section>
      <title>Meta-model used</title>
      <para> Two metamodels are used on these Selection and Product Derivation engine : </para>
      <para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The feature meta-model presented on the following figure : </para>
            <para><inlinegraphic fileref="PTech_figures/featureDiagram.png"/></para>
            <para>For more information about it please refer to the Feature Diagram Editor
              Documentation.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>the resolution model that store selected and unselected features as presented on
              the following figure : </para>
            <para><inlinegraphic fileref="PTech_figures/ResolutionMetamodel.png"/></para>
            <para>Note that Attribute, FeatureDiagram and Feature meta-classes are meta-classes of
              featureDiagram metamodel. The enumeration SelectionState permits to know if a feature
              is selected or not.</para>
            <para/>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title> Choices about variability</title>
      <para>Two ways can be used to derive the base model ( model on which elements were added on
        the derived feature model) :</para>
      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Positive variability</emphasis>: we create a new empty model
              as resolved model and we add on it base model elements associated with selected
              features. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Negative variability</emphasis>: we create a copy of the
              base model and remove on it base model elements associated with unselected
              feature.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist> We use the negative variability for the current version. In a next version
        we will combine both positive and negative variability. </para>
      <important>
        <title> Negative variability remove only domain model elements associated with unselected
          features</title>
        <para> Product derivation with negative variability remove only domain model elements
          associated with unselected features. All other elements stay in the resolved model.</para>
      </important>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title> Test of Selection and Product Derivation Engine</title>
    <para>Derivation tests are available on the project<emphasis role="bold">
        fr.inria.featureDiagramEditor.fdext.ui.tests</emphasis>. To retrieve this project go
        to<emphasis role="italic"> File</emphasis>-><emphasis role="italic"> New</emphasis>
        -><emphasis role="italic"> Example</emphasis> -><emphasis role="italic">Product Derivation
        Sample</emphasis> -> <emphasis role="italic">Product Derivation Test</emphasis>. Then you
      can open the<emphasis role="italic"> Design Perspective</emphasis> and click on the session
      files (.aird) and open it.</para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title> Conclusion</title>
    <para> This document has presented the technical documentation and the tests of the selection
      and product derivation . This is a first version that will be completed.</para>
  </chapter>
</book>
